Cornelius Marius Schoonmaker Papers
Manuscript Division, Library of Congress
Cornelius Marius Schoonmaker Papers 1833-1931 (bulk 1860-1890)
MSS52944
Schoonmaker, Cornelius Marius, 1839-1889
1,400 items
4 containers
1.6 linear feet
Manuscript Division, Library of Congress Washington, D.C.
Naval officer. Correspondence, letterbook, order book, printed matter, scrapbooks, and unpublished biography detailing Schoonmaker’s naval career. Of particular interest are Schoonmaker’s letters regarding China and the Far East, accounts of the battle of Mobile Bay, and details of his death in Samoa.
Selected Search Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the LC Catalog. They are grouped by name of person or organization, by subject or location, and by occupation and listed alphabetically.
People
Chandler, William E. (William Eaton), 1835-1917--Correspondence.; Dahlgren, John Adolphus Bernard, 1809-1870--Correspondence.; Dornin, Thomas A. (Thomas Aloysius), 1800-1874--Correspondence.; Farragut, David Glasgow, 1801-1870--Correspondence.; Goldsborough, Louis Malesherbes, 1805-1877--Correspondence.; Howell, John Cumming, 1819-1892--Correspondence.; Robeson, George M. (George Maxwell), 1829-1897--Correspondence.; Schoonmaker, Cornelius Marius, 1839-1889.; Thompson, Richard W. (Richard Wigginton), 1809-1900--Correspondence.; Toucey, Isaac, 1796-1869--Correspondence.; Welles, Gideon, 1802-1878--Correspondence.; Whitney, William C. (William Collins), 1841-1904--Correspondence.
Organizations
Polaris (Ship); Vandalia (Screw sloop)
Subjects
Mobile Bay, Battle of, Ala., 1864.
Places
Alabama--History--Civil War, 1861-1865.; China--Description and travel.; East Asia--Description and travel.; United States--History--Civil War, 1861-1865--Campaigns.
Occupations
Naval officers.
Provenance
The papers of Cornelius Marius Schoonmaker, naval officer, were deposited in the Library of Congress by the Naval Historical Foundation in 1950. The collection was converted to gift in 1998.
Access and Restrictions
The papers of Cornelius Marius Schoonmaker are open to research. Researchers are advised to contact the Manuscript Reading Room prior to visiting. Many collections are stored off-site and advance notice is needed to retrieve these items for research use.
Biographical Note
Date Event
1839, Feb. 2 Born, Kingston, N.Y.
1859 Graduated, United States Naval Academy, Annapolis, Md. Duty on the San Jacinto (screw frigate), African Squadron
1860 Duty on the Falmouth (brig)
1861 Executive master, Minnesota (steam frigate)
1862 1864 Executive officer, Octorara (gun boat), West Gulf Blockading Squadron
1864 Executive officer, Manhattan (iron clad), West Gulf Blockading Squadron
1865 Duty on the Catskill (iron clad)
1867 1868 Executive officer, Juniata (steam sloop), South Atlantic Squadron
1869 1870 Executive officer, Delaware (screw steamer), Asiatic Squadron
1871 Married Matilda Rogers Cooper
1872 1873 Commanded the Frolic (side wheeled steamer)
1873 Duty at the Brooklyn Navy Yard, Brooklyn, N.Y.
1874 Duty as inspector of 8th Lighthouse District, New Orleans, La.
1879 1881 Commanded the Nipsic (steam sloop), European Squadron
1882 Duty at the Norfolk Navy Yard, Norfolk, Va.
1886 Promoted to captain
1888 1889 Commanded the Vandalia (screw sloop)
1889, Mar. 15 Died, Apia, Samoa
Scope and Content Note
The papers of Cornelius Marius Schoonmaker (1839-1889) span the years 1833-1931, with the bulk of the material concentrated in the period 1860-1890. Correspondence, a letterbook, a night order book, scrapbooks, and a manuscript of a biography of Schoonmaker constitute the collection. The correspondence is official and covers nearly all of Schoonmaker’s orders to duty and cruises. Of interest in the correspondence is George M. Robeson’s letter of May 15, 1873, ordering Schoonmaker to cruise to Newfoundland and to bring the survivors of the Polaris (screw tug) to Washington, D.C.
Correspondents include William E. Chandler, John Adolphus Bernard Dahlgren, Thomas A. Dornin, David Glasgow Farragut, Louis Malesherbes Goldsborough, John C. Howell, Richard W. Thompson, Issac Toucey, Gideon Welles, and William C. Whitney.
Schoonmaker’s biography, written by his father, Marius Schoonmaker, includes copies of letters to family and friends concerning Schoonmaker’s tours of duty, an account of his service in the Civil War, and a description of his death by drowning in a hurricane which also wrecked his ship, the Vandalia.
Arrangement of the Papers
This collection is arranged alphabetically by type of material.
Container List
- Correspondence, 1857-1931, (12 folders) (Box 1)
- Genealogy, undated (Box 1)
- Letterbook, Nipsic (steam sloop), 1879-1881 (Box 1)
- Night order book, Nipsic (steam sloop), 1879-1881 (Box 1)
- Printed matter, 1833-1889, undated (Box 2)
- Scrapbooks, 1863-1909, (2 vols.) (Box 2)
- “Thirty-Four Years in the United States Navy; Life and Correspondence of Captain C. Marius Schoonmaker, United States Navy,” by Marius Schoonmaker (father), undated (Box 3)
  - Holograph draft, (2 vols.) (Box 3)
  - Holograph and typed drafts, (14 folders) (Box 4)
- Watch, quarter, and station bills, Juniata (screw sloop), 1867-1868 (Box 4)